RG 093, Selective Service System, State Headquarters
Connecticut State Library
Selective Service System State Headquarters records
1940-1975
Connecticut State Library
United States. Selective Service System. Connecticut
19 cubic feet
President Franklin Roosevelt signed the Selective Training and Service Act of 1940 (Public Law 783), which created the country’s first peacetime draft and formally established the Selective Service System as an independent Federal agency. From 1948 until 1973, during both peacetime and periods of conflict, men were drafted to fill vacancies in the armed forces that could not be filled through voluntary means. In 1973, the draft ended and the United States converted to an all-volunteer military. The registration requirement was suspended in April 1975 but was resumed again in 1980.
RG093
T002769
Historical Note
President Franklin Roosevelt signed the Selective Training and Service Act of 1940 (Public Law 783), which created the country’s first peacetime draft and formally established the Selective Service System as an independent Federal agency. On October 7 of that year, the first local Selective Service boards were appointed in Connecticut. From 1948 until 1973, during both peacetime and periods of conflict, men were drafted to fill vacancies in the armed forces that could not be filled through voluntary means. In 1973, the draft ended and the United States converted to an all-volunteer military. The registration requirement was suspended in April 1975. It was resumed again in 1980 by President Carter and continues today.
Scope and Content
The records of Connecticut’s Headquarters of the Selective Service System documents the various activities of the local boards and such committees as the Youth Advisory Committee, State Medical Advisory Committee, Advisory Committee on Scientific, Engineering, and Specialized Personnel, and the Industry Advisory Committee. Records include manuals, procedural directives, statistical reports, requests for draft deferments, newspaper clippings, publications, meeting minutes, and correspondence.
Related Material
RG 005:029, Raymond E. Baldwin, Jr. gubernatorial records, Box 473.
RG 005:030, McConaughy/Shannon gubernatorial records, Box 518.
RG 005:032, John Davis Lodge gubernatorial records, Box 581.
RG 005:035, Thomas Meskill gubernatorial records, Box A-667.
RG 022, Department of Economic and Community Dvelopment. Scrapbooks pertaining to first peacetime draft, 1940-1941.
Index Terms
Organizations:
United States. Selective Service System. Connecticut
Subjects:
United States. Selective Service System. Connecticut -- Records and correspondence; United States -- Armed Forces -- Recruiting, enlistment, etc.; Draft registration -- United States
Document Types:
Correspondence; Minutes; Clippings; Membership lists; Manuals (instructional materials); Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The records were transferred to the State Archives on May 7, 1976.
Container List
- Records, 1940-1975
  - 1. Selective Service System Manuals, 1940-1968; 10 notebooks (Box 1)
    Included are published form manuals, regulations, and laws.
  - 2. Procedural Directive Issuances, 1940-1973 (Box 2-3)
    Copies of memoranda issued to local draft boards.
    Arranged chronologically by year, and thereafter alphabetically by subject.
  - 3. Connecticut Selective Service Statistical Reports, 1948-1970 (Box 4-5)
    Included are monthly records of deliveries (of draftees), Inductions and examinations, medical rejections, reports on the availability of physicians, dentists and veterinarians, and summaries of classifications.
    Arranged chronologically.
  - 4. Records of the Youth Advisory Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    Pursuant to instructions of the federal government, the State Directors of the Selective Service established the Youth Advisory Committee on July 1, 1969. The Committee was directed to provide information and advice to the State Director, concerning the views and attitudes of youthful members of society toward Selective Service laws and their administration.
    The records consist of materials pertaining to the formation of the Committee, organization and membership, minutes of meetings, and project reports.
  - 5. Records of the Connecticut State Medical Advisory Committee, 1950-1957 (Box 5)
    Membership records, correspondence sampling and miscellaneous material.
  - 6. Records of the Advisory Committee on Scientific, Engineering, and Specialized Personnel, 1955-1971 (Box 5-6)
    Minutes of meetings and sampling of correspondence.
  - 7. Records of the Industry Advisory Committee, 1952-1964 (Box 6)
    Minutes of meetings.
  - 8. Conscientious Objector Manual, 1952-1962 (Box 6)
    Treatment of cases involving conscientious objectors.
  - 9. Registered and Unregistered Apprentice Training Program Acceptances Requests, 1952-1971 (Box 6)
    Requests for draft deferments on the basis of participation in an approved apprenticeship training program.
    Arranged numerically by form number.
  - 10. Records relating to emergency evacuations, 1948-1972
    - Emergency Decentralization Plans, Catastrophe Plans and releated materials, 1948-1972 (Box 7-8)
    - Operation Alert Exercises and related mobilization data, 1955-1961 (Box 9)
  - 11. Training Materials, 1962-1975 (Box 10-12)
    Materials used in training Selective Service personnel. Included are lesson plans, slides, transparencies, and miscellaneous materials.
    Unarranged.
  - 12. Miscellaneous Material, 1943-1974 (Box 13)
  - 13 Publications, 1947-1975 (Box 14-15)
  - 14. Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1975
    - 1940 October-1941 March, 1 volume (Volume Item 16)
    - 1948 March-1950 January, 1 volume (Volume Item 17)
    - 1950 July-1950 December, 1 volume (Volume Item 18)
    - 1950 December-1956 December, 1 volume (Volume Item 19)
    - 1956 October-1963 January, 1 volume (Volume Item 20)
    - 1963 February-1967 March, 1 volume (Volume Item 21)
    - 1966 March-1970 April, 1 volume (Volume Item 22)
      Also includes envelope of clippings dated July 1970-November 1970.
    - 1970 December-1975, 4 separate envelopes tied together (Volume Item 23)